# Uthaipon "Tao" Tantipongpipat

# Machine Learning Engineer / Al Researcher

Orlando, FL, US uthaipon@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/uthaipon/

#### **SUMMARY**

Machine learning researcher at Twitter in responsible AI / AI ethics. Has driven successful projects (resulting in 3+ billions press click-read) and led company-wide engineers in applying research based on company data. Track record (10+) of top-tier computer science (ML/AI/Statistics) publications. A PhD from Georgia Tech focused on ML theory, optimization, with 1st place award from the US government on differential privacy.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Twitter, remote US** - Machine Learning Researcher

Jun 2020 - PRESENT

- Led Twitter's image cropping algorithmic bias audit resulting in a published academic paper and \$1.5M press ad equivalency and 3B readership from 500 news articles in 49 countries. Led to another follow-up work by team members resulted in additional \$1.4M,
   2.7B reads, and 800 articles from 47 additional countries, and contributed to the decision to remove the algorithm in production
- Proposed a 13-18% precision-recall video classification model improvement with no additional cost to partnering team to fix offensive misclassifications on Tweet topic annotations, and discovered correlation bias with demographics despite a lack of private individual data
- Established a data-driven guideline for company-wide engineers to adopt a inequality metric in A/B statistical testing, as well as winning business approval with company leadership that finally led to shipping the metric
- Provided statistical analysis to customer teams to evaluate and quantify bias in ML models;
   redesigned common ML statistical significance tests required for bias measurement
- Mentored a junior researcher
- Published two papers in social computing conference and one in data science journal

## Microsoft, Redmond WA - Research Intern

May 2019 - July 2019

- Implemented privacy guarantee on large-scale natural language processing models (RNNs and LSTMs) to protect against personal deidentification due to model usage
- Developed novel correlation clustering algorithm with corresponding privacy analysis
- Researched private submodular optimization and surveyed literature for private stochastic gradient descent for improving training deep learning models
- Published one paper in the machine learning conference NeurlPS

## **EDUCATION**

# Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta GA

PhD in Algorithms, Combinatorics, and Optimization (ACO)

Aug 2016 - May 2020

Minor in Computational Learning Theory. GPA 4.00/4.00

# University of Richmond, Richmond VA

BS in Mathematics, Honors with Thesis (Algebraic Combinatorics)

Aug 2012 - May 2016

Minor in Computer Science. GPA 3.97/4.00

# University of Oxford, Oxford UK

Study Abroad Program in Mathematics and Computer Science Oct 2014 - Jun 2015

# **AWARDS**

#### **Academic:**

•	Impact Recognition Award, CSCW (the social computing conference)	2021
•	ACO Outstanding Student Award (best PhD student in the year at the graduation)	2020
•	Best Reviewers of NeurlPS (top-tier machine learning conference)	2019
•	Full-merit 4-year scholarship for tuition and living expense, University of Richmond 20	12 - 2016

#### **Competitions:**

•	et Prize Award and People's Choice Award (\$20,000 total), The Unlinkable Data Challenge,	
	National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), US Department of Commerce	2018
•	Finalist, Tech Challenge programming competition, Illinois Technology Association, IL	2016
•	<b>2nd Place</b> , ICPC Mid-Atlantic USA Regional Contest, Christopher Newport University	2015
•	Honorable Mention (top 2.5%), William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition	2015
•	Bronze Medal and Honorable Mention, Asia-Pacific Mathematics Olympiad (APMO) 2010, 2011	
•	Gold and Bronze Medals, IWYMIC International Mathematics Competition 200	08, 2009

# **PUBLICATIONS**

I have 11 peer-reviewed published papers, mainly in top-tier CS venues (such as NeurIPS, COLT, SODA). Topics include machine learning, responsible ML (fairness in ML), differential privacy, fairness, algorithms/theory, statistics, and Human-Centered Interaction (HCI)/Social Computing. My website <a href="https://www.uthaipon.com">www.uthaipon.com</a> or <a href="mailto:Google Scholar">Google Scholar</a> has full details.

## **SKILLS**

Technical: Python, Java, C++, SQL (BigQuery), Pytorch, pandas, numpy, scipy, Git, CVXOPT,

MATLAB, Mathematica, LaTeX, MS Office

Languages: Thai (native); English (full proficiency)